Guide to the Samuel B. Parsons, Jr. Papers 1862-1962 (bulk, 1877-1920s) MS 3153
New-York Historical Society
Samuel B. Parsons, Jr. papers
1862-1962 (bulk, 1877-1920s)
New-York Historical Society
Parsons, Samuel, 1844-1923
MS 3153
3.3 Linear feet in 4 document boxes and one flat box
The collection includes a variety of documents related to landscape architect Samuel B. Parsons Jr. (1844-1923). The documents principally concern his involvement with New York City's Parks Department and Central Park, for which he was Superintendent of Planting under Calvert Vaux and later Landscape Architect (from about 1880-1911). There are also several corporate records of the privately-held firms Samuel Parsons & Sons and Samuel Parsons, Inc. In connection with Central Park, the collection holds photographs and diagrams related to the restoration of elm trees on the Mall, a typescript of testimony taken during Raymond B. Fosdick's 1911 investigation into the Parks Department accounts, a draft resolution of exoneration of Parsons by the Parks Board, and a scrapbook and manuscript "memories," both of which largely concern the Park. In addition the collection also holds several letters from Parsons written to his father while the son was in service during the Civil War with the U.S. Sanitary Commission; a lecture by Parsons with suggestions for landscaping a country home; published works by Parsons; a volume of extracts taken by Parsons of books he read; genealogical notes; photographs of the grounds of various estates; and other documents.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged roughly by format, with correspondence and other manuscript material opening the inventory, followed by financial records, scrapbooks, book extracts, photographs, and published material.
Biographical / Historical
Samuel Bowne Parsons Jr. (1844-1923) was a landscape architect who, most relevant to this collection, was responsible as Superintendent of Planting and later Landscape Architect for the New York City Parks Department from about 1880 to 1911. In that post he was engaged especially with Central Park and was consequently embroiled in many disputes over the appropriate usage and development of the Park, which eventually led to his removal as Landscape Architect.
Parsons's grandfather was a horticulturalist and founded a nursery in Flushing, Queens, Long Island around 1840. That business was known as Samuel Parsons & Sons (one of the sons being Parsons's father) and was handed down through the family until its dissolution about 1907. Parsons learned the trade as a youngster before serving with the U.S. Sanitary Commission during the Civil War and then graduating from the Sheffield Scientific School at Yale in 1865. He moved out on his own, buying a farm, and developing his skills as a landscape architect. He came into the orbit of Calvert Vaux (1824-1895) and, when Vaux became Landscape Architect for the New York City Parks Department in 1880, he had Parsons named Superintendent of Planting. After Vaux's death, Parsons replaced him as Landscape Architect until 1911. Aside from his official New York City responsibilities, Parsons also worked on other projects during and after his tenure, including the design of Balboa Park in San Diego around 1902.
Parsons married Martha Francis in 1865 and they had a daughter, Mabel. Mabel briefly carried on Parsons's business after his death and published a book of the "memories" he had drafted late in his life. Parsons died in 1923 at his home in the San Remo apartments, on Central Park West, directly across the street from the Park. He is buried in Woodlawn Cemetery.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Cogswell Limited Partnership, 2020.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes a variety of documents related to Samuel Parsons, especially concerning his involvement with New York City's Central Park and the corporate records of the privately-held firms Samuel Parsons & Sons and Samuel Parsons, Inc. In connection with Central Park, the collection holds photographs and diagrams related to the restoration of elm trees on the Mall, a typescript of testimony taken during Raymond B. Fosdick's 1911 investigation into the Parks Department accounts, a draft resolution of exoneration of Parsons by the Parks Board, and a scrapbook and manuscript "memories," both of which largely concern the Park.
The collection also holds several letters from Parsons written to his father while the son was in service during the Civil War with the U.S. Sanitary Commission; a lecture by Parsons with his suggestions for landscaping a country home; published works by Parsons; a volume of extracts taken by Parsons of books he read; genealogical notes; photographs of the grounds of various estates; and other documents. The container list below includes a full inventory of the content.
Landscape architects -- New York (State); Landscape architecture -- United States.; Central Park (New York, N.Y.); United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Financial records.; Letters (correspondence).; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; New York (N.Y.). Department of Parks; Parsons & Sons Co.; United States Sanitary Commission
- Civil War era documents, 1862-1864, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes 10 letters from Parsons to his father, written in late 1862 while in service with the U.S. Sanitary Commission. Writing from Washington, Sharpsburg, Harpers Ferry, and New Bern (North Carolina), Parsons makes various observations on the conditions of the soldiers and the management of the Commission's operation. He also notes various positive impressions of Frederick Olmsted. The folder also includes two items possibly by Parsons: an essay about German poet Ulrich von Hutten (1488-1523) and a fictional(?) tale of a woman's near drowning while ice skating in Central Park that (spoiler alert) leads to marriage with her rescuer. Also two letters to Parsons from a friend, Lieutenant Henry V.D. Stone of the 2nd Massachusetts Infantry, writing in 1863 from Virginia, and a letter from Stone's brother informing Parson's of Stone's death at Gettysburg. Also, a letter from Clarence (Clarence R. King according to the donor), written from the Sierra Nevada and discussing King's increased spirituality; "the Bishop of Oxford's puzzle"; and a poem to S.P by M.P (1864).
- "Dedication Ode" by Parsons, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Although the specific context is unidentified, it appears to be the dedication of a cemetery or other burial site.
- "The most promising new hardy ornamental trees and shrubs, and their most tasteful and effective arrangement" by Parsons, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Printed copies of Parsons's prize essay delivered before the Massachusetts Horticultural Society.
- List of "Maps and studies of parks in the borough of Manhattan by Samuel Parsons", undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Saw the city [San Diego] from Point Loma", circa 1902 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Newspaper clipping of an article written by Parsons describing his drive with Mr. Marston to Point Loma.
- "Memories of Samuel Parsons," typescript, with edits by Mabel Parsons, circa 1918?-1924 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Typescript of approximately 146 pages that is likely a manuscript of the book published by Mabel Parsons in 1924. It is missing the first two pages and an unknown number at the end (missing pages were not in the papers when they were donated to N-YHS). The subject matter primarily concerns Central Park and Parsons's memoirs of his involvement with the Park beginning about 1880 as Superintendent of Planting and later Superintendent of Parks. He describes his relationship with and favorable impressions of Calvert Vaux; his opinions of the various successful and unsuccessful attempts to add sculpture and other ornamentation and facilities to Central Park (e.g., racetrack, Metropolitan Museum of Art, zoo/menagerie, a bid for a World's Fair, etc.); observations and disagreements about landscaping and his efforts to improve the Park; the contributions of Mrs. Russell Sage, Andrew Green, and others to the Park; placement of the St. Gaudens statue of General Sherman; and the efforts to remove him from office. There is also a chapter on Morningside Park and on Parsons's observations of parks during a European tour.
- "An old vlissengen farm: The quaint Quaker house that John Bowne built for his wife in 1661", circa 1880s? (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Includes a 3 page description of the "family house" at Flushing, Queens, Long Island, likely written by Parsons. This is the John Bowne House, which still stands as of 2020 and is the oldest surviving house in Queens.
- Samuel Parsons lecture, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  117 page typescript of lecture to unidentified audience of "ladies and gentlemen" concerning landscaping of one's country home, including site selection, placement of house and walkways, grading, fencing, and planting of lawn, shrubs, flowers, etc.
- Parks Department. Typescript. "In the matter of an examination of the accounts and methods of the Department of Parks, Borough of Manhattan" (2 folders), 1911 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  Various individuals testify before Commissioner Fosdick, including Parsons; his testimony is on pages 188-228.
- Resolution of exoneration, circa 1911 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Includes several draft resolutions for the Park Board expressing its regret for the removal of Parsons as Superintendent in 1911.
- Death-related documents, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Includes copy of the letter sent by George Gordon Battle, president of the Parks and Playgrounds Association, to the City Editor of the New York Times paying tribute to the memory of Parsons; a handwritten transcript, possibly by Mabel, of the obituary in the Evening Post; receipt for payment of a lot at Woodlawn Cemetery; and several small newspaper clippings/obituaries.
- Mary Parsons estate. Abstract of title (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Martha Parsons. Correspondence, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  One letter, in draft and typed, from Martha (Mrs. Samuel Parsons) to Green-Wood Cemetery concerning a dispute over the inheritance of two lots, with Green-Wood's acknowledgement.
- Mabel Parsons. Letters and notes, 1927-1962 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Includes 6 items: two letters from William W. Cook complimenting Mabel on the publication of "Memories" and noting that the book's rhododendron episode occurred on Cook's place and noting that he had sent her gratis a copy of his book "American institutions and their preservation" (1927); a letter of genealogical information from Kate S. Doty (1958); two notes by Mabel of genealogical information (1962); and a note of regret from Barnard College that Mabel would be unable to attend a luncheon due to an accident (1962).
- Mabel Parsons. Red Cross, 1947-1955 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Includes lists of contributors (1951-55) and a certificate of appreciation (1947).
- Central Park map, 1959, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Two copies of a map of the park, dated 1959, apparently mailed to Mabel Parsons in 1961.
- Parsons & Sons. Stock certificate book, 1877-1907 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Parsons & Sons. List of stockholders, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Parsons & Sons. Meeting minutes, 1877-1903 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Minute book also includes annual financial data.
- Parsons & Sons. Official papers, 1904-1907 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Includes meeting announcements, proxy notices, director resignations, stock ownership inquiries, and some minutes.
- Parsons & Sons. Bill of sale, 1905 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Memorandum of agreement and bill of sale of various trees and other plants to Parsons & Sons by Rosalie C. Campbell of Eden, Maine.
- Parsons & Sons. Business & financial statements, 1904-1909 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Also includes documents related to the firm's dissolution in 1908. The 1909 financial statement is for Samuel Parsons in business after Parsons & Sons dissolution.
- Samuel Parsons Inc. Stock certificate books (2), 1916-1922 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Samuel Parsons Inc. Corporate documents, 1916-1925 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Includes documents related to the formation of the corporation in 1916, including certificate of incorporation, by-laws, and subsequent amendments; minutes of the Board of Directors up to the dissolution in 1925; form of stock certificates; stock subscriptions; plan of reorganization; meeting notices and waivers; proxies; and letters related to the continuation of the business after Parsons's death in 1923.
- Samuel Parsons Inc. Business & financial statements, 1918, 1922-1923 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Scrapbook, circa 1919-1927 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  All newspaper clippings in fragile condition. Appears to all relate to Central Park.
- Scrapbook, 1890s-1920s (Box 2, Volume 2)
  Clippings concern Central Park, Parsons career in New York and elsewhere, Catholicism in relation to school funding, and other topics.
- Samuel Parsons. Extracts of books read by Parsons. Vol. I. (2 copies), undated (Box 2, Volume 3-4)
  An attached note to the volumes reads: "Copy of Vol. I of Series of 13 Volumes, entitled History, Religion, Miscellaneous, of Extracts of Books read by Samuel Parsons and given to New York Public Library, April 1924, as Samuel Parsons' Note Books." This first volume includes an index to all 13 volumes plus extracts of the following works: Lord Acton's letters to Gladstone's daughter, Mary; G.K. Chesterton's short history of England; 3 works of English history by J.S. Corbett; Maurice Milloud's "The Ruling Castle and Frenzied Trade in Germany"; Ramsay Muir's "National Self-Government"; G. Elliot Smith's "The Ancient Egyptians"; and D.A. Winstanley's "Lord Chatham and the Whig Opposition."
- Photograph. Estate of William A. Butler, Yonkers NY. View of pergola, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Photo by A.B. Phelan.
- Photograph. Albemarle Park, Asheville, NC. Houses and grounds, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Photo by Lindsey & McFarland.
- Drawing. "Topography below dam in Frederick T. Proctor Park, Utica, N.Y.", 1915 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  Drawn by civil engineer Clifford Lewis, Jr.
- Photograph. Central Park. Mall?, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Photo by Helm Studios.
- Photographs. Estate of John G. Agar, Premium Point, New Rochelle, NY, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Most photos stamped as taken by John Weiss, Inc. About 16 photos, plus some duplicates, of the grounds, rock wall at the shore of Long Island Sound, walkway, driveway, garden, gate, bridge, etc.
- Photographs. Estate of Henry L. Blum, White Plains, NY, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Photos by John Weiss, Inc. 6 photos of grounds, garden, driveway, and garden structures.
- Photographs. Estate of Charles E. Diefenthaler, New Canaan, Conn., undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Photographer not identified. About 9 photos of garden house, walkways, garden, and grounds.
- Photographs. Estate of William W. Cook, Esq., Portchester, NY, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Photos by William Hale Kirk. Photos (and one postcard) of rock wall and driveway entrance.
- Photographs. Estate of A. Pagenstecher Jr., Cornwall-on-Hudson, NY (2 folders), undated (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
  Photographer not identified. About 6 photos, plus duplicates, of driveways and grounds. 2nd folder holds one negative of the entrance to the estate.
- Photographs. Estate of Mrs. Charles H. Senff, Whitestone, Long Island, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Most photos noted as by Harry Healy. About 9 photos of driveway and grounds.
- Photographs. Estate of Francis Lynde Stetson, Skylands, Sterlington, NY, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Photos by Helm Studios. About 6 photos, plus duplicates, of pond, grounds, and buildings.
- Photograph. Unidentified building and pond/grounds, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Photoreproduction. Plate from book, depicting William A. Stiles, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Photograph album. Skylands, 1919 (Box 5, Volume 1)
  12 photos of building and grounds, with captions on slip of paper at front.
- Photograph album. Central Park. The Mall, 1894 (Box 5, Volume 2)
  The album is labeled as relating to the Central Park Mall. It includes a drawing of the tree-lined Mall in 1894, with 3 photographs of houses and elm trees clearly not in Central Park, but suggestive of influences in one direction or another.
- Photograph album. Central Park and other, circa 1919 (Box 5, Volume 3)
  A portfolio of loose photographs and other graphic material. The core centers on the Central Park Mall in 1919, including comparative photos of the Mall in 1862 and 1918, and diagrams showing proposed restoration of the elms on the Mall and their then status as planted. Several other photos of grounds not in Central Park seem to be illustrative of what the proposed elms would eventually grow to become; these include the Nicholas Brady estate at Roslyn, Long Island, and other unidentified places. There are some photographs that might be unrelated, including rhododendrons and spruces adjoining the formal garden of the estate of Clarence H. Mackay at Roslyn, and the Weir Bridge on the State Reservation at Niagara (1896).
- Published works. "Concerning lawn planting" by Calvert Vaux and Parsons, 1881 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Published works. Central Park, 1883, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  Includes 2 items: article reprints concerning the resolution to move the zoological collection/menagerie north of the Park's Reservoir, and about 10 pages from a pictorial work about the Park.
- Published works. "Monograph on The Evergreens, a rural cemetery, Brooklyn, N.Y.", 1891 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Publicity/marketing booklet
- Published works. Scribner's Magazine with article "The Evolution of a City Square" by Parsons, 1892 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Published works. Scribner's Magazine with article "Small Country Places" by Parsons, 1892 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Published works. Scribner's Magazine with article "The Landscape Features of the Paris Exposition" by Parsons, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Published works. "Report to Park Board, New York City, on visit to European parks" by Parsons, 1906 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  Several copies of report in original envelope.
- Published works. "English House Grounds", 1924 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  Photographic views compiled and published by Parsons's daughter, Mabel Parsons, and dedicated to Samuel, accomplishing the work he had originally conceived and laid groundwork for. Text by Clarence Fowler.